ILGWU. James Lipsig papers, 5780/126
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. James Lipsig papers
1946-1970
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Lipsig, James.
5780/126
1 cubic feet
1 linear foot
Records
Contains correspondence, testimony, and other material relating to James Lipsig's work as Assistant Executive Secretary of the ILGWU. Also included are minutes of the Finance Committee and the Education Committee.
5518055
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
June 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, June 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
After working as general counsel for the Textile Workers of America, James Lipsig served as Assistant Executive Secretary of the ILGWU for thirty years. Throughout his career, Lipsig also served as secretary of the Socialist Party of New York State, as board member of the Jewish Labor Committee, the National Sharecroppers' Fund and the National Jewish Community Relations Advisory, and as a consultant to the Workers Defense League. Born in New York City, Lipsig was a graduate of City College and Columbia University Law School. He died in New York City on December 18, 1976 at the age of 66.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, testimony, and other material relating to James Lipsig's work as Assistant Executive Secretary of the ILGWU. Also included are minutes of the Finance Committee and the Education Committee.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
5780/082. ILGWU. James Lipsig papers
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; People with disabilities -- United States; Displaced workers -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- United States; Lipsig, James.; Lipsig, James.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5518055
- Long Branch Account. Forgery Case., 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Arbitration, 1946-192 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Immigration. Skilled Garment Workers, 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Civil Liberties Questions, 1947-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Complaints by Members, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Local 105 Subcommittee, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous Materials Prepared, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ILGWU General Office and Office Employees International Union (OEIU) Local 153 Contracts, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Union Health Center Committee, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Scope and Contents
  Minutes and Correspondence
- Goldberg Campaign, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Convention Arrangements, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Florence Novitsky, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Office Employees International Union (OEIU) Local 153
- New York City Center Trades Labor Council, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Local 25. Vacation Fund and Federal Taxes, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Wage Stabilization, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Economic Control Bulletin no.1,5-31.
- Upper South Health and Welfare Funds and Unemployment Insurance, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Local 132. Health and Welfare Funds, 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Union Broadcasting Corp., 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Finance Committee. Minutes, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Education Committee, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Immigration Matter. Kaufman, Ralph (Kozak), 1937-1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Radio Stations [folder 1 of 2], 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Radio Stations [folder 2 of 2], 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)